<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
   <properties>
      <title>AnnoCultor Core</title>
      <author>Borys Omelayenko</author>
   </properties>
   <body>
     <!-- fix remove update add -->          
      <release version="2.3.11" description="Adapting to Europeana.eu workflow">  
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="fix">
               Place tagger does not add coordinates for countries, 
               as they typically point to some middle point. 
           </action>               
      </release>
       <!-- 2.3.2 -->
      <release version="2.3.2" date="2010-10-01" description="SOLR datasource, merge files with SPARQL, ontology subtractor for maintenance of large RDF files ">  
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Lookup rules can fetch terms by URI. Typically, we want to fetch concept URI by label, 
               but sometimes we know the URI and want to fetch terms' labels.
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               SOLR server as a datasource. Data from a running SOLR server can be converted, 
               the same way as databases/SQL, ontologies/SPARQL, and XML files.
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               It is often necessary to add/remove a few statements from the large generated RDF files.
               New feature OntologySubtractor that allows removing statements from an RDF file (to-be-removed-from) 
               that are stated in another RDF file (statements-to-be-removed).  
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               SparqlQueryHelper allows merging a few RDF files (also just-generated conversion results)
               with an SPARQL statement. Very convenient if the generated file needs to be augmented with some statements
               from other RDf files.
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               HierarchyTracingFilter reads a file with top concepts, goes through a bunch of RDF data files and
               lists all direct or indirect skos:narrower concepts in a separate file, thus making an exhaustive list
               of all children of the top concepts.  
           </action>               
      </release>  
      <!-- 2.3.1 -->
      <release version="2.3.1" description="Properties File destination, improved build procedure">  
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Destination PropertiesFile allows storing subject-value pairs in .properties files.
               This is handy if these files are then loaded for further processing. 
           </action>               
      </release>  
      <!-- 2.3.0 -->
      <release version="2.3.0" description="Scalable for Europeana">  
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Destination RdfGraphSwapNames stored RDF files with
               swapped parts of the name. Useful if destinations are assigned dynamically
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Parameter $ANNOCULTOR_DATASOURCE_ITERATOR_10 in a query
               converts it to ten queries, where $ANNOCULTOR_DATASOURCE_ITERATOR_10
               is replaced with 0 to 9. Made for the use case when a query result is too
               large to fit RAM
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="remove">
               Keeping previous copy of RDF and compare it to the current. 
               This feature was not used, and DIFF with a version control systems are more useful
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Multiple queries are allowed in SQL and SPARQL data sources
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Converter parameters are loaded first from annocultor.properties file
               then from environment, and then the yet not set properties are completed
                with default values
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Record Filters: if conversion result uses a few terms from a vocabulary
               then it allows creating a shorter version of this vocabulary with 
               the terms that are used
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Flexible data destination. Possibility to
               extend the RdfDestinationFile with custom destination formats
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Flexible datasource. In addition to the built-in XML, SQL, SPARQL, 
               custom implementations of DataSource interface may be plugged-in
               to work with custom source formats
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Redesigned (XPath-like) path matching routines to achieve nearly 100-fold speed increase.
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Redesigned how statistics are collected to make conversion reports. 
               It used to go out of memory on a few Gb of converted files. 
               Now swaps large chunks of statistics data to disk and runs with reasonable memory needs.
               Prepared for porting statistics to a database 
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Added SPARQL datasource. Can now convert data coming from XML files, SQL or SPARQL queries.
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Converter for Europeana ESE format, originally meant to run enrichment. 
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Person name disambiguation utilities (see Europeana ESE converter). 
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Place disambiguation utilities (see Europeana ESE converter). 
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Enrichment links are given readable comments. 
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="fix">
               Fixed encoding issue with parsing Geonames singe-file-dump into per-country RDF files. 
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="fix">
               Handling of xml:lang.
           </action>               
      </release>    

       <!-- 2.2.4 -->
      <release version="2.2.4" description="XPath">  
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Support for XPath attr queries
           </action>               
      </release>    
      <release version="2.2.3" description="eu.annocultor">  
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Move to eu.annocultor packages
           </action>               
      </release>    
      <release version="2.2.2" description="Production and Java 6">  
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Handling cascading xml:lang
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Moved to Java 6 and the Java 6 built-in way of invoking Java Compiler there
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Splitting RDF files into volumes of 300.000 triples. Volume number is added to generated RDF file names
           </action>               
      </release>    
      <release version="2.2" description="Maintenance">  
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Dynamic load of tools.jar from environment variable
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Generated URLs. Made them stricter
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="fix">
               Path expressions. Qualified attributes
           </action>               
      </release> 
      <release version="2.1" description="XML format for defining converters">  
            <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Conversion progress report: records passed, memory used
           </action>               
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Detector of rubbish terms in vocabulary lookup rules and warning. If unlucky, they may seriously deteriorate system performance. 
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="update">
               Performance improvements on computing XML paths
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Major change: XML API: converters are written in XML (with occasional small snippets of Java code)
           </action>                    
      </release>
      <release version="1.4 final" date="2008-07-28" description="Final release of version 1">              
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="fix">
		On failure Converter.run returns -1 that can be returned by the main methods to let maven see that it has failed
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
               Maven build
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		Separate XML files can be merged and processed with a single converter run
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		Local.build.properties file allows setting build properties for ant build (e.g. -Xmx) 
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		Build numbers in both build system and source
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		Local file annocultor.properties may override environment properties and ANNOCULTOR_HOME
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		New conversion report generated into the /doc directory 
           </action>         
      </release>
      <release version="1.3" date="2008-07-28" description="Europeana summer release">   
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		streaming conversion, flat memory profile, but vocabularies are stored in memory
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		all tests are automaticallt extracted
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		Path allows expressions like element[attr='value' and attr='value'] in queries
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		Path allows expressions like element@attr in queries returning attribute value
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		Environment stores a number of directories
           </action>         
           <action dev="omelayenko" type="add">
		Conversion stores the RDF to be overwritten into /prev, after conversion it does a diff stored in /diff
           </action>         
       </release>         
   </body>
</document>
